<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="water_resource">WATER SOURCES</string>
    <string name="water_resource_content">Almost any environment has water present to some degree. Possible sources of water in various environments are listed below. Information on how to make the water potable is provided as well.\n\n

NOTE: If you do not have a canteen, cup, can, or other type of container, improvise one from plastic or water-resistant cloth. Shape the plastic or cloth into a bowl by pleating it. Use pins or other suitable items—even your hands—to hold the pleats.\n\n

Heavy dew can provide water. Tie rags or tufts of fine grass around your ankles and walk through dew-covered grass before sunrise. As the rags or grass tufts absorb the dew, wring the water into a container. Repeat the process until you have a supply of water or until the dew is gone. Australian natives sometimes mop up as much as 1 liter an hour this way.\n\n

Bees or ants going into a hole in a tree may point to a water-filled hole. Siphon the water with plastic tubing or scoop it up with an improvised dipper. You can also stuff cloth in the hole to absorb the water and then wring it from the cloth.\n\n

Water sometimes gathers in tree crotches or rock crevices. Use the above procedures to get the water. In arid areas, bird droppings around a crack in the rocks may indicate water in or near the crack.\n\n

Green bamboo thickets are an excellent source of fresh water. Water from green bamboo is clear and odorless. To get the water, bend a green bamboo stalk, tie it down, and cut off the top (Figure 6-3). The water will drip freely during the night. Old, cracked bamboo may also contain water.\n\n</string>


    <string name="water_6_3_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_3pic_title">Figure 6-3. Water From Green Bamboo</string>


    <string name="water_6_4_content">Wherever you find banana trees, plantain trees, or sugarcane, you can get water. Cut down the tree, leaving about a 30-centimeter (12-inch) stump, and scoop out the center of the stump so that the hollow is bowl-shaped. Water from the roots will immediately start to fill the hollow. The first three fillings of water will be bitter, but succeeding fillings will be palatable. The stump (Figure 6-4) will supply water for up to 4 days. Be sure to cover it to keep out insects.\n\n</string>


    <string name="water_6_4_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_4pic_title">Figure 6-4. Water From Plantain or Banana Tree Stump</string>


    <string name="water_6_5_content">Some tropical vines can give you water. Cut a notch in the vine as high as you can reach, then cut the vine off close to the ground. Catch the dropping liquid in a container or in your mouth (Figure 6-5).\n\n</string>

    <string name="water_6_5_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_5pic_title">Figure 6-5. Water From a Vine</string>

    <string name="water_othertree_content">The following trees can also provide water:\n\n

\u2022 Palms. The buri, coconut, sugar, rattan, and nips contain liquid. Bruise a lower frond and pull it down so the tree will "bleed" at the injury.\n
\u2022Traveler tree. Found in Madagascar, this tree has a cuplike sheath at the base of its leaves in which water collects.\n
\u2022 Umbrella tree. The leaf bases and roots of this tree of western tropical Africa can provide water.\n
\u2022 Baobab tree. This tree of the sandy plains of northern Australia and Africa collects water in its bottlelike trunk during the wet season. Frequently, you can find clear, fresh water in these trees after weeks of dry weather.\n</string>

    <string name="water_still">STILL CONSTRUCTION</string>
    <string name="water_still_content">You can use stills in various areas of the world. They draw moisture from the ground and from plant material. You need certain materials to build a still, and you need time to let it collect the water. It takes about 24 hours to get 0.5 to 1 liter of water.</string>


    <string name="water_above_title">ABOVEGROUND STILLS</string>
    <string name="water_above1_content">You can construct two types of aboveground stills. To make the vegetation bag still, you need a sunny slope on which to place the still, a clear plastic bag, green leafy vegetation, and a small rock (Figure 6-6).\n\n</string>


    <string name="water_6_6_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_6pic_title">Vegetation Bag Still</string>


    <string name="water_above2_content">To make a still image, you should:
Fill the bag with air by turning the opening towards the breeze or by scooping air into the bag.
Fill the plastic bag with one-half to three-quarters of the leafy plants. Be sure to remove all hard sticks or spikes that might pierce the bag.
Put a small stone or similar object in the bag.
 Close the bag and tie the mouth of the bag as close to the end of the bag as possible to maintain the maximum air space. If you have a tube, a small straw, or a hollow reed, please insert one end into the mouth of the bag first, and then fasten it tightly. Then fasten or plug the tube to prevent air from escaping. This tube allows you to drain the condensate without opening the bag.
Place the bag mouth downhill and place it on a sunny slope. Place the mouth of the bag slightly above the low point of the bag.
Secure the bag in place so that the rock enters the low point of the bag by itself.
To remove the condensed water from the distiller, loosen the tie around the mouth of the bag and tilt the bag so that the water collected around the rocks can drain. Then re-tighten the mouth and reposition the distiller to allow further condensation.
After extracting most of the water from the bag, replace the vegetation in the bag. This will ensure the maximum output of water.
Making transpiration bags is still similar to vegetation bags, but easier. Simply tie the plastic bag to the leafy branch with the tube inserted, and then tie the mouth of the bag tightly around the branch to form an airtight seal. Tie the ends of the limbs so that they hang below the mouth of the bag. Water will gather there.</string>

    <string name="water_6_7_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_7pic_title"> Water Transpiration Bag</string>

    <string name="water_above3_content">The same limb may be used for 3 to 5 days without causing long-term harm to the limb. It will heal itself within a few hours of removing the bag.\n\n</string>


    <string name="water_below_title">BELOWGROUND STILL</string>
    <string name="water_below1_content">To make a belowground still, you need a digging tool, a container, a clear plastic sheet, a drinking tube, and a rock (Figure 6-8).\n\n</string>

    <string name="water_6_8_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_8pic_title">Figure 6-8. Belowground Still</string>

    <string name="water_below2_content">Choose a location where you think the soil contains moisture (such as a dry river bed or a low place where rainwater is collected). The soil at the site should be easy to excavate, and sunlight must reach the site most of the day.

To build a still image, you should:

 Dig a bowl-shaped hole approximately 1 meter (3 feet) wide and 60 cm (24 inches) deep.
 Dig a puddle in the center of the hole. The depth and circumference of the sink depend on the size of the container you must put in it. The bottom of the sump should allow the container to stand upright.
 Secure the pipe to the bottom of the container by forming a loose overhand knot in the pipe.
 Put the container upright in the sink.
 Place the unanchored end of the tube up, over, and beyond the edge of the hole.
 Place a plastic sheet on the hole and cover its edge with mud to hold it in place.
Place a stone in the center of the plastic sheet.
Put the plastic sheet into the hole until it is about 40 cm (16 inches) from the ground. It now forms an inverted cone with the rock at its apex. Make sure that the apex of the cone is directly above your container. Also make sure that the plastic cone does not touch the sides of the hole, because the earth will absorb the condensed water.
Put more dirt on the edge of the plastic to hold it firmly in place and prevent moisture loss.
 Plug the tube when not in use to prevent water evaporation and prevent insects from entering.

Using the tube as a straw, you can drink water without disturbing the distiller. By opening the distiller, you can release the accumulated humid and warm air.

You may want to use the plants in the holes as a source of moisture. If so, dig out additional soil from both sides of the hole to form a slope and place plants on it. Then follow the above operations.

If sewage is the only source of moisture, dig a small groove outside the hole about 25 cm (10 inches) from the lip of the distiller (Figure 6-9). Dig a trench approximately 25 cm (10 inches) deep and 8 cm (3 inches) wide. Pour sewage into the tank. Make sure not to spill any contaminated water on the edge of the hole in the plastic sheet that touches the soil. The water tank holds the sewage, and the soil filters it when the distiller sucks the sewage. The water then condenses on the plastic and drains into the container. This process is very effective when your only water source is salt water.</string>
    <string name="water_6_9_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_9pic_title">Figure 6-9. Belowground Still to Get Potable Water From Polluted Water</string>

    <string name="water_below3_content">You will need at least three stills to meet your individual daily water intake needs. In comparison to the belowground still and the water transpiration bag still, the vegetation bag produces the best yield of water.\n\n</string>








    <!-- next page -->
    <string name="water_pure">WATER PURIFICATION</string>
    <string name="water_pure_content">Rainwater collected in clean containers or in plants is usually safe for drinking. However, purify water from lakes, ponds, swamps, springs, or streams, especially the water near human settlements or in the tropics.\n\n

When possible, purify all water you get from vegetation or from the ground by boiling or using iodine or chlorine. After purifying a canteen of water, you must partially unscrew the cap and turn the canteen upside down to rinse unpurified water from the threads of the canteen where your mouth touches.\n\n

Purify water by the following methods:\n\n

\u2022 If you are lucky you packed a filter like the LifeStraw as part of your Kit\n
\u2022 Use water purification tablets. (Follow the directions provided.)\n
\u2022 Place 5 drops of 2 percent tincture of iodine in a canteen full of clear water. If the canteen is full of cloudy or cold water, use 10 drops. (Let the canteen of water stand for 30 minutes before drinking.)\n
\u2022 Use 2 drops of 10 percent (military strength) povidone-iodine or 1 percent titrated povidone-iodine. The civilian equivalent is usually 2 percent strength, so 10 drops will be needed. Let stand for 30 minutes. If the water is cold and clear, wait 60 minutes. If its very cold or cloudy, add 4 drops and wait 60 minutes.\n
\u2022 Place 2 drops of chlorine bleach (5.25 percent sodium hypochlorite) in a canteen of water. Let stand 30 minutes. If the water is cold or cloudy, wait 60 minutes. Remember that not all bleach is the same around the world; check the available level of sodium hypochlorite.\n
\u2022 Use potassium permanganate, commonly marketed as Condys Crystals, for a number of applications, including emergency disinfection of water. The crystals are of a nonuniform size, so you must judge the actual dosage by the color of the water after adding the crystals. Add three small crystals to 1 liter (1 quart) of water. If the water turns a bright pink after waiting 30 minutes, the water is considered purified. If the water turns a dark pink, there is too much potassium permanganate to drink safely. Either add more water to dilute the mixture or save it for use as an antiseptic solution. If the water becomes a full red, like the color of cranberry juice, the solution may be used as an antifungal solution.\n
\u2022 Boil your drinking water. This is the safest method of purifying your drinking water. By achieving a rolling boil, you can ensure that you are destroying all living waterborne pathogens.\n\n


By drinking nonpotable water you may contract diseases or swallow organisms that can harm you and may easily lead to potentially fatal waterborne illnesses.\n\n

Two of the most prevalent pathogens found in most water sources throughout the world are:\n\n

\u2022 Giardia, which causes Giardiasis (beaver fever). It is characterized by an explosive, watery diarrhea accompanied by severe cramps lasting 7 to 14 days.\n
\u2022 Cryptosporidium, which causes Cryptosporidiosis. It is much like Giardiasis, only more severe and prolonged, and there is no known cure but time. Diarrhea may be mild and can last from 3 days to 2 weeks.\n\n


NOTE: The only effective means of neutralizing Cryptosporidium is by boiling or by using a commercial microfilter or reverse-osmosis filtration system. Chemical disinfectants such as iodine tablets or bleach have not shown to be 100 percent effective in eliminating Cryptosporidium.\n\n

Examples of other diseases or organisms are:\n\n

\u2022 Dysentery. You may experience severe, prolonged diarrhea with bloody stools, fever, and weakness.\n
\u2022 Cholera and typhoid. You may be susceptible to these diseases regardless of inoculations. Cholera can cause profuse, watery diarrhea, vomiting, and leg cramps. Typhoid symptoms include fever, headache, loss of appetite, constipation, and bleeding in the bowel.\n
\u2022 Hepatitis A. Symptoms include diarrhea, abdominal pain, jaundice, and dark urine. This infection can spread through close person-to-person contact or ingestion of contaminated water or food.\n
\u2022 Flukes. Stagnant, polluted water—especially in tropical areas—often contains blood flukes. If you swallow flukes, they will bore into the bloodstream, live as parasites, and cause disease.\n
\u2022 Leeches. If you swallow a leech, it can hook onto the throat passage or inside the nose. It will suck blood, create a wound, and move to another area. Each bleeding wound may become infected.\n\n</string>











    <!-- next page -->
    <string name="water_device">WATER FILTRATION DEVICES</string>
    <string name="water_device1_content">If the water you find is also muddy, stagnant, and foul-smelling, you can clear the water:\n\n

\u2022 By placing it in a container and letting it stand for 12 hours.\n
\u2022 By pouring it through a filtering system.\n\n
NOTE: These procedures only clear the water and make it more palatable. You will have to purify it.\n\n

To make a filtering system, place several centimeters or layers of filtering material such as sand, crushed rock, charcoal, or cloth in bamboo, a hollow log, or an article of clothing (Figure 6-10).\n\n</string>



    <string name="water_6_10_title">pic needed</string>
    <string name="water_6_10pic_title">Figure 6-10. Water Filtering Systems</string>


    <string name="water_device2_content">Remove the odor from water by adding charcoal from your fire. Charcoal is also helpful in absorbing some agricultural and industrial chemicals. Let the water stand for 45 minutes before drinking it.\n\n</string>









</resources>