<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="medical_basic">Basic</string>
    <string name="medical_title_main">REQUIREMENTS FOR MAINTENANCE OF HEALTH</string>
    <string name="medical_title_main_content">To survive, you need water and food. You must also have and apply high personal hygiene standards.\n</string>

    <string name="medical_water_title">Water</string>
    <string name="medical_water_content" tools:ignore="TypographyOther">
        Your body loses water through normal body processes (sweating, urinating, and defecating). During average daily exertion when the atmospheric temperature is 20 degrees Celsius (C) (68 degrees Fahrenheit [F]),
        the average adult loses 2 to 3 liters of water. Other factors can cause your body to lose more water, such as heat exposure, cold exposure, intense activity, high altitude, burns, or illness. You must replace this water.
        \n\nDehydration results from inadequate replacement of lost body fluids. It decreases your efficiency and, if you are injured, it increases susceptibility to severe shock. Consider the following results of body fluid loss:
        \n
        \u2022 A 5-percent loss results in thirst, irritability, nausea, and weakness.\n
        \u2022 A 10-percent loss results in dizziness, headache, inability to walk, and a tingling sensation in the limbs.\n
        \u2022 A 15-percent loss results in dim vision, painful urination, swollen tongue, deafness, and a numb feeling in the skin.\n
        \u2022 A loss greater than 15 percent may result in death.\nThe most common signs and symptoms of dehydration are:\n
        \u2022 Dark urine with a very strong odor (Generally, the darker the urine, the more dehydrated you are).\n
        \u2022 Low urine output.\n
        \u2022 Dark, sunken eyes.\n
        \u2022 Fatigue.\n
        \u2022 Emotional instability.\n
        \u2022 Loss of skin elasticity.\n
        \u2022 Delayed capillary refill in fingernail beds.\n
        \u2022 Trench line down center of tongue.\n
        \u2022 Thirst (Last on the list because you are already 2-percent dehydrated by the time you crave fluids).\n
        \nYou should replace water as you lose it. Trying to make up a deficit is difficult in a survival situation, and thirst is not a sign of how much water you need.\n
        \nMost people cannot comfortably drink more than 1 liter of water at a time. So, even when not thirsty, drink small amounts of water at regular intervals each hour to prevent dehydration.\n
        \nIf you are under physical and mental stress, or subject to severe conditions, increase your water intake. Drink enough liquids to maintain a urine output of at least 0.5 liters every 24 hours. Urine color is one indicator of hydration levels.\n
        \nIn any situation where food intake is low, drink 6 to 8 liters of water per day. In an extreme climate, especially an arid one, the average person can lose 2.5 to 3.5 liters of water per hour. In this type of climate, you should drink 8 to 12 ounces of water every 30 minutes.
        It is better to regulate water loss through work or rest cycles because overhydration can occur if water intake exceeds 1.5 quarts per hour. Overhydration can cause low serum sodium levels resulting in cerebral and pulmonary edema, which can lead to death.\n
        \nWith the loss of water there is also a loss of electrolytes (body salts). The average diet can usually keep up with these losses, but in an extreme situation or illness, additional sources are necessary. You should maintain an intake of carbohydrates and other necessary electrolytes.\n
        \nYou can make an Oral Rehydration Salts (ORS) drink to replace lost salts after severe diarrhea or vomiting by mixing 0.5 teaspoons of salt and 2 tablespoons of sugar in 1 liter of water. Recommended amounts to drink vary by body mass:\n
        \u2022 Babies and infants (0-2 years): 0.5 liters every 24 hours\n
        \u2022 Children (2-9 years): 1 liter every 24 hours\n
        \u2022 Older children and adults: 3 liters every 24 hours\n
        \nOf all the physical problems encountered in a survival situation, the loss of water is the most preventable. The following are basic guidelines for the prevention of dehydration:\n
        \u2022 Always drink water when eating. Water is used as a part of the digestion process and can lead to dehydration.\n
        \u2022 Acclimatize. The body performs more efficiently in extreme conditions when acclimatized.\n
        \u2022 Conserve sweat, not water. Limit sweat-producing activities but drink water.\n
        \u2022 Ration water. Until you find a suitable source, ration your sweat, not your water. Limit activity and heat gain or loss.\n
        \nYou can estimate fluid loss by several means. A field dressing holds about 0.25 liters (1/4 canteen) of fluid. A soaked T-shirt holds 0.5 to 0.75 liters.\n
        \nYou can also use the pulse and breathing rate to estimate fluid loss. Use the following as a guide:\n
        \u2022 With a 0.75-liter loss the wrist pulse rate will be under 100 beats per minute and the breathing rate 12 to 20 breaths per minute.\n
        \u2022 With a 0.75 to 1.5-liter loss the pulse rate will be 100 to 120 beats per minute and 20 to 30 breaths per minute.\n
        \u2022 With a 1.5 to 2-liter loss the pulse rate will be 120 to 140 beats per minute and 30 to 40 breaths per minute. Vital signs above these rates require advanced care.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_food_title">Food</string>
    <string name="medical_food_content">
        Although you can live several weeks without food, you need an adequate amount to stay healthy. Without food your mental and physical capabilities will deteriorate rapidly and you will become weak. Food provides energy and replenishes the substances that your body burns.
        Food provides vitamins, minerals, salts, and other elements essential to good health. And, possibly more important, it helps morale.\n
        \nThe three basic sources of food are plants, animals (including fish) and fungus. In varying degrees, these provide the calories, carbohydrates, fats, and proteins needed for normal daily body functions. You should use rations to augment plant and animal foods,
        which will extend and help maintain a balanced diet.\n
        \nCalories are a measure of heat and potential energy. The average person needs 2,000 calories per day to function at a minimum level. An adequate amount of carbohydrates, fats, and proteins without an adequate caloric intake will lead to starvation and cannibalism of the body\'s own tissue for energy.
        It may be useful to estimate your TDEE (Total Daily Energy Expenditure) since each individual requires different caloric minimums.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_plants_title">Plants</string>
    <string name="medical_plants_content">
        Plant foods provide carbohydrates—the main source of energy. Many plants provide enough protein to keep the body at normal efficiency. Although plants may not provide a balanced diet, they will sustain you even in the arctic, where meat\'s 
        heat-producing qualities are normally essential. Many plant foods such as nuts and seeds will give you enough protein and oils for normal efficiency. Roots, green vegetables, and plant foods containing natural sugar will provide calories and carbohydrates that give the body natural energy.\n
        \nThe food value of plants becomes more and more important if you are eluding enemies or if you are in an area where wildlife is scarce. For instance:\n
        \u2022 You can dry plants by wind, air, sun, or fire. This retards spoilage so that you can store or carry the plant food with you to use when needed.\n
        \u2022 You can often obtain plants more easily than meat.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_animals_title">Animals</string>
    <string name="medical_animals_content">
        Meat is more nourishing than plant food. It may even be more readily available in some places. However, to get meat, you need to know the habits of (and how to capture) the various wildlife.\n
        \nTo satisfy immediate food needs, first seek the more abundant and easily obtained wildlife. This includes insects, crustaceans, mollusks, fish, and reptiles. These can satisfy hunger while you are preparing traps and snares for larger game.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_personal_hygiene_title">PERSONAL HYGIENE</string>
    <string name="medical_personal_hygiene_content">
        Cleanliness is always an important factor in preventing infection and disease. This becomes even more important in a survival situation since poor hygiene can reduce chances of survival.\n
        \nA daily shower with hot water and soap is ideal, but you can stay clean without this luxury. Use a cloth and soapy water to wash yourself. Pay special attention to the feet, armpits, crotch, hands, and hair as these are prime areas for infestation and infection. If water is scarce, take an "air" bath.
        Remove as much of your clothing as practical and expose your body to the sun and air for at least 1 hour. Be careful not to sunburn.\n
        \nIf you don\'t have soap, use ashes or sand, or make soap from animal fat and wood ashes if your situation allows. To make soap:\n
        \u2022 Extract grease from animal fat by cutting the fat into small pieces and cooking it in a pot.\n
        \u2022 Add enough water to the pot to keep the fat from sticking as it cooks.\n
        \u2022 Cook the fat slowly, stirring frequently.\n
        \u2022 After the fat is rendered, pour the grease into a container to harden.\n
        \u2022 Place ashes in a container with a spout near the bottom.\n
        \u2022 Pour water over the ashes and collect the liquid that drips out of the spout in a separate container. This liquid is the potash or lye.\n
        \nAnother way to get the lye is to pour the slurry (the mixture of ashes and water) through a straining cloth.\n
        \u2022 In a cooking pot, mix two parts grease to one part lye.\n
        \u2022 Place this mixture over a fire and boil it until it thickens.\n
        \nAfter the mixture (the soap) cools, you can use it in the semiliquid state directly from the pot. You can also pour it into a pan, allow it to harden, and cut it into bars for later use.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_hands_clean_title">Keep Your Hands Clean</string>
    <string name="medical_hands_clean_content">
        Germs on your hands can infect food and wounds. Wash your hands after handling any material that is likely to carry germs, after urinating or defecating, after caring for the sick, and before handling any food, food utensils, or drinking water.
        Keep your fingernails closely trimmed and clean, and keep your fingers out of your mouth.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_hair_clean_title">Keep Your Hair Clean</string>
    <string name="medical_hair_clean_content">
        Hair can become a haven for bacteria, fleas, lice, and other parasites. Keeping your hair clean, combed, and trimmed helps you avoid this danger.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_cloth_clean_title">Keep Your Clothing Clean</string>
    <string name="medical_cloth_clean_content">Keep your clothing and bedding as clean as possible to reduce the chances of skin infection or parasitic infestation. Clean your outer clothing whenever it becomes soiled. Wear clean underclothing and socks each day. If water is scarce, "air" clean your clothing by shaking, airing, and sunning it for 2 hours.
        If you are using a sleeping bag, turn it inside out after each use, fluff it, and air it.\n</string>
    <string name="medical_teeth_clean_title">Keep Your Teeth Clean</string>
    <string name="medical_teeth_clean_content">
        Thoroughly clean your mouth and teeth with a toothbrush at least once each day. If you don\'t have a toothbrush, make a chewing stick. Find a twig about 20 centimeters (cm) (8 inches) long and 1 centimeter (1/3 inch) wide. Chew one end of the stick to separate the fibers. Then brush your teeth thoroughly.
        Another way is to wrap a clean strip of cloth around your fingers and rub your teeth with it to wipe away food particles. You can also brush your teeth with small amounts of sand, baking soda, salt, or soap. Rinse your mouth with water, salt water, or willow bark tea. Flossing your teeth with string or fiber also helps oral hygiene.\n
        \nIf you have cavities, you can make temporary fillings by placing candle wax, tobacco, hot pepper, toothpaste or powder, or portions of a gingerroot into the cavity. Make sure you clean the cavity by rinsing or picking the particles out of the cavity before placing a filling in the cavity.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_care_feet_title">Take Care of Your Feet</string>
    <string name="medical_care_feet_content">
        To prevent serious foot problems, break in your shoes before wearing them on any mission. Wash and massage your feet daily. Trim your toenails straight across. Wear an insole and the proper size of dry socks. Powder and check your feet daily for blisters.\n
        \nIf you get a small blister, do not open it. An intact blister is safe from infection. Apply a padding material around the blister to relieve pressure and reduce friction. If the blister bursts, treat it as an open wound. Clean and dress it daily and pad around it. Leave large blisters intact. To avoid having the blister burst or tear under pressure and cause a painful and open sore, do the following:\n
        \u2022 Obtain a sewing-type needle and a clean or sterilized thread.\n
        \u2022 Run the needle and thread through the blister after cleaning the blister.\n
        \u2022 Detach the needle and leave both ends of the thread hanging out of the blister. The thread will absorb the liquid inside. This reduces the size of the hole and ensures that the hole does not close up.\n
        \u2022 Pad around the blister.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_rest_title">Get Sufficient Rest</string>
    <string name="medical_rest_content">
        You need a certain amount of rest to keep going. Plan for regular rest periods of at least 10 minutes per hour during your daily activities. Learn to make yourself comfortable under less-than-ideal conditions. A change from mental to physical activity or vice versa can be refreshing when time or situation does not permit total relaxation.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_campsite_clean_title">Keep Campsite Clean</string>
    <string name="medical_campsite_clean_content">
        Do not soil the ground in the campsite area with urine or feces. Use latrines, if available. When latrines are not available, dig "cat holes" and cover the waste. Collect drinking water upstream from the campsite. Purify all water.
    </string>


    <string name="medical_emergency">Medical Emergencies</string>
    <string name="medical_emergency_title">MEDICAL EMERGENCIES</string>
    <string name="medical_emergency_content">
        Medical problems and emergencies you may face include breathing problems, severe bleeding, and shock. The following paragraphs explain each of these problems and what you can expect if they occur.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_breathing_title">BREATHING PROBLEMS</string>
    <string name="medical_breathing_content">
        Any one of the following can cause airway obstruction, resulting in stopped breathing:\n
        \u2022 Foreign matter in mouth or throat which obstructs the opening to the trachea.\n
        \u2022 Face or neck injuries.\n
        \u2022 Inflammation and swelling of mouth and throat caused by inhaling smoke, flames, irritating vapors, or by an allergic reaction.\n
        \u2022 "Kink" in the throat (caused by the neck bent forward so that the chin rests upon the chest).
        \u2022 Tongue blocks passage of air to the lungs upon unconsciousness. When an individual is unconscious, the muscles of the lower jaw and tongue relax as the neck drops forward. This causes the lower jaw to sag and the tongue to drop back and block the passage of air.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_bleeding_title">SEVERE BLEEDING</string>
    <string name="medical_bleeding_content">
        Severe bleeding from any major blood vessel in the body is extremely dangerous. The loss of 1 liter of blood will produce moderate symptoms of shock. The loss of 2 liters will produce a severe state of shock that places the body in extreme danger. The loss of 3 liters is usually fatal.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_shock_title">SHOCK</string>
    <string name="medical_shock_content">
        Shock (acute stress reaction) is not a disease in itself. It is a clinical condition characterized by symptoms that arise when cardiac output is insufficient to fill the arteries with blood under enough pressure to provide an adequate blood supply to the organs and tissues.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_lifesaving_steps_title">LIFESAVING STEPS</string>
    <string name="medical_lifesaving_steps_content">
        Control panic, both your own and the victim\'s. Reassure him and try to keep him quiet. Perform a rapid physical exam. Look for the cause of the injury and follow the ABCs of first aid. Start with the airway and breathing, but be discerning.
        In some cases, a person may die from arterial bleeding more quickly than from an airway obstruction. The following paragraphs describe how to treat airway, bleeding, and shock emergencies.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_airway_title">OPEN AIRWAY AND MAINTAIN</string>
    <string name="medical_airway_content">
        You can open an airway and maintain it by using the following steps:\n
        \u2022 Step 1. You should check to see if the victim has a partial or complete airway obstruction. If he can cough or speak, allow him to clear the obstruction naturally. Stand by, reassure the victim, and be ready to clear his airway and perform mouth-to-mouth resuscitation should he become unconscious. If his airway is completely obstructed, administer abdominal thrusts until the obstruction is cleared.\n
        \u2022 Step 2. Using a finger, quickly sweep the victim\'s mouth clear of any foreign objects, broken teeth, dentures, and sand.\n
        \u2022 Step 3. Using the jaw thrust method, grasp the angles of the victim\'s lower jaw and lift with both hands, one on each side, moving the jaw forward. For stability, rest your elbows on the surface on which the victim is lying. If his lips are closed, gently open the lower lip with your thumb.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_figure_4_1">Figure 4–1. Jaw Thrust Method</string>
    <string name="medical_note">
        NOTE: Cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) may be necessary after cleaning the airway, but only after major bleeding is under control. See FM 21-20, Physical Fitness Training, the American Heart Association manual, the Red Cross manual, or most other first aid books for detailed instructions on CPR.\n\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_control_bleeding_title">CONTROL BLEEDING</string>
    <string name="medical_control_bleeding_content">
        In a survival situation, you must control serious bleeding immediately because replacement fluids normally are not available and the victim can die within a matter of minutes. External bleeding falls into the following classifications (according to its source):\n\n

        \u2022 Arterial. Blood vessels called arteries carry blood away from the heart and through the body. A cut artery issues bright red blood from the wound in distinct spurts or pulses that correspond to the rhythm of the heartbeat. Because the blood in the arteries is under high pressure, an individual can lose a large volume of blood in a short period when damage to an artery of significant size occurs. Therefore, arterial bleeding is the most serious type of bleeding. If not controlled promptly, it can be fatal.\n
        \u2022 Venous. Venous blood is blood that is returning to the heart through blood vessels called veins. A steady flow of dark red, maroon, or bluish blood characterizes bleeding from a vein. You can usually control venous bleeding more easily than arterial bleeding.\n
        \u2022 Capillary. The capillaries are the extremely small vessels that connect the arteries with the veins. Capillary bleeding most commonly occurs in minor cuts and scrapes. This type of bleeding is not difficult to control.\n\n
        You can control external bleeding by direct pressure, indirect (pressure points) pressure, elevation, digital ligation, or tourniquet. Each method is explained below.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_direct_pressure_title">Direct Pressure</string>
    <string name="medical_direction_pressure_content">
        The most effective way to control external bleeding is by applying pressure directly over the wound. This pressure must not only be firm enough to stop the bleeding, but it must also be maintained long enough to "seal off" the damaged surface.\n\n

        If bleeding continues after having applied direct pressure for 30 minutes, apply a pressure dressing. This dressing consists of a thick dressing of gauze or other suitable material applied directly over the wound and held in place with a tightly wrapped bandage (Figure 4-2). It should be tighter than an ordinary compression bandage but not so tight that it impairs circulation to the rest of the limb. Once you apply the dressing, do not remove it, even when the dressing becomes blood soaked.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_figure_4_2">Figure 4–2. Application of a Pressure Dressing</string>
    <string name="medical_pressure_point_title">Pressure Points</string>
    <string name="medical_pressure_point_content">
        A pressure point is a location where the main artery to the wound lies near the surface of the skin or where the artery passes directly over a bony prominence (Figure 4-3). You can use digital pressure on a pressure point to slow arterial bleeding until the application of a pressure dressing. Pressure point control is not as effective for controlling bleeding as direct pressure exerted on the wound. It is rare when a single major compressible artery supplies a damaged vessel.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_figure_4_3">Figure 4–3. Pressure Points</string>
    <string name="medical_tourniquet_title">Tourniquet</string>
    <string name="medical_tourniquet_content">
        Use a tourniquet only when direct pressure over the bleeding point and all other methods did not control the bleeding. If you leave a tourniquet in place too long, the damage to the tissues can progress to gangrene, with a loss of the limb later.
        An improperly applied tourniquet can also cause permanent damage to nerves and other tissues at the site of the constriction. If you must use a tourniquet, place it around the extremity, between the wound and the heart, 5 to 10 centimeters (2 to 4 inches) above the wound site. Never place it directly over the wound or a fracture. Figure 4-4 explains how to apply a tourniquet.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_figure_4_4">Figure 4–4. Application of Tourniquet</string>
    <string name="medical_bone_title">Bone and Joint Injury</string>
    <string name="medical_fractures_title">FRACTURES</string>
    <string name="medical_fracture_content">
        There are basically two types of fractures: open and closed. With an open (or compound) fracture, the bone protrudes through the skin and complicates the actual fracture with an open wound. Any bone protruding from the wound should be cleaned with an antiseptic and kept moist. You should splint the injured area and continually monitor blood flow past the injury. Only reposition the break if there is no blood flow.

        The closed fracture has no open wounds. Follow the guidelines for immobilization and splint the fracture.\n

        The signs and symptoms of a fracture are pain, tenderness, discoloration, swelling deformity, loss of function, and grating (a sound or feeling that occurs when broken bone ends rub together).\n

        The dangers with a fracture are the severing or the compression of a nerve or blood vessel at the site of fracture. For this reason minimum manipulation should be done, and only very cautiously. If you notice the area below the break becoming numb, swollen, cool to the touch, or turning pale, and the victim showing signs of shock, a major vessel may have been severed. You must control this internal bleeding. Reset the fracture, treat the victim for shock, and replace lost fluids.\n

        Often you must maintain traction during the splinting and healing process. You can effectively pull smaller bones such as the arm or lower leg by hand. You can create traction by wedging a hand or foot in the V-notch of a tree and pushing against the tree with the other extremity. You can then splint the break.\n

        Strong muscles hold a broken thighbone (femur) in place making it difficult to maintain traction during healing. You can make an improvised traction splint using natural material (Figure 4-6) as explained below.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_figure_4_6">Figure 4–6. Improvised Traction Splint</string>
    <string name="medical_dislocations_title">DISLOCATIONS</string>
    <string name="medical_dislocations_content">
        Dislocations are the separations of bone joints causing the bones to go out of proper alignment. These misalignments can be extremely painful and can cause an impairment of nerve or circulatory function below the area affected. You must place these joints back into alignment as quickly as possible.\n

        Signs and symptoms of dislocations are joint pain, tenderness, swelling, discoloration, limited range of motion, and deformity of the joint. You treat dislocations by reduction, immobilization, and rehabilitation.\n

        Reduction or "setting" is placing the bones back into their proper alignment. You can use several methods, but manual traction or the use of weights to pull the bones are the safest and easiest. Once performed, reduction decreases the victim\'s pain and allows for normal function and circulation. Without an X ray, you can judge proper alignment by the look and feel of the joint and by comparing it to the joint on the opposite side.\n

        Immobilization is nothing more than splinting the dislocation after reduction. You can use any field-expedient material for a splint or you can splint an extremity to the body. The basic guidelines for splinting are as follows:\n

        \u2022 Splint above and below the fracture site.
        \u2022 Pad splints to reduce discomfort.
        \u2022Check circulation below the fracture after making each tie on the splint.
        \nTo rehabilitate the dislocation, remove the splints after 7 to 14 days. Gradually use the injured joint until fully healed.
    </string>
    <string name="medical_sprains_title">SPRAINS</string>
    <string name="medical_sprains_content">
        The accidental overstretching of a tendon or ligament causes sprains. The signs and symptoms are pain, swelling, tenderness, and discoloration (black and blue).

        When treating sprains, you should follow the letters in RICE as defined below:\n

        \u2022 R-Rest injured area.\n
        \u2022I-Ice for 24 to 48 hours.\n
        \u2022C-Compression-wrap or splint to help stabilize. If possible, leave the boot on a sprained ankle unless circulation is compromised.\n
        \u2022E-Elevate the affected area.\n
        NOTE: Ice is preferred for a sprain but cold spring water may be more easily obtained in a survival situation.
    </string>
    <string name="medical_bites_title">Bites and Stings</string>
    <string name="medical_bites_content">
        Insects and related pests are hazards in a survival situation. They not only cause irritations, but they are often carriers of diseases that cause severe allergic reactions in some individuals. In many parts of the world you will be exposed to serious, even fatal, diseases not encountered in the United States.\n

        \u2022 Ticks can carry and transmit diseases, such as Rocky Mountain spotted fever common in many parts of the United States. Ticks also transmit Lyme disease.\n
        \u2022 Mosquitoes may carry malaria, dengue, and many other diseases.\n
        \u2022 Flies can spread disease from contact with infectious sources. They are causes of sleeping sickness, typhoid, cholera, and dysentery.\n
        \u2022 Fleas can transmit plague.\n
        \u2022 Lice can transmit typhus and relapsing fever.\n
        The best way to avoid the complications of insect bites and stings is to keep immunizations (including booster shots) up-to-date, avoid insect-infested areas, use netting and insect repellent, and wear all clothing properly.\n

        \nIf you are bitten or stung, do not scratch the bite or sting, it might become infected. Inspect your body at least once a day to ensure there are no insects attached to you. If you find ticks attached to your body, cover them with a substance (such as petroleum jelly, heavy oil, or tree sap) that will cut off their air supply.
        Without air, the tick releases it\'s hold, and you can remove it. Take care to remove the whole tick. Use tweezers if you have them. Grasp the tick where it\'s mouthparts are attached to the skin. Do not squeeze the tick\'s body. Wash your hands after touching the tick. Clean the tick wound daily until healed.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_bite_treatment_title">TREATMENT</string>
    <string name="medical_bite_treatment_content">
        It is impossible to list the treatment of all the different types of bites and stings. However, you can generally treat bites and stings as follows:\n\n

        \u2022 If antibiotics are available for your use, become familiar with them before deployment and use them.\n
        \u2022 Predeployment immunizations can prevent most of the common diseases carried by mosquitoes and some carried by flies.\n
        \u2022 The common fly-borne diseases are usually treatable with penicillins or erythromycin.\n
        \u2022 Most tick, flea, louse, and mite-borne diseases are treatable with tetracycline.\n
        \u2022 Most antibiotics come in 250 milligram (mg) or 500 mg tablets. If you cannot remember the exact dose rate to treat a disease, 2 tablets, 4 times a day, for 10 to 14 days will usually kill any bacteria. (80 to 112 tablets total.)\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_bees_sting_title">BEE AND WASP STINGS</string>
    <string name="medical_bees_sting_content">
        If stung by a bee, immediately remove the stinger and venom sac, if attached, by scraping with a fingernail or a knife blade. Do not squeeze or grasp the stinger or venom sac, as squeezing will force more venom into the wound. Wash the sting site thoroughly with soap and water to lessen the chance of a secondary infection.\n

        If you know or suspect that you are allergic to insect stings, always carry an insect sting kit with you.\n

        Relieve the itching and discomfort caused by insect bites by applying:\n

        \u2022 Cold compresses.\n
        \u2022 A cooling paste of mud and ashes.\n
        \u2022 Sap from dandelions.\n
        \u2022 Coconut meat.\n
        \u2022 Crushed cloves of garlic.\n
        \u2022 Onion.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_spider_bites_title">SPIDER BITES AND SCORPION STINGS</string>
    <string name="medical_spider_bites_content">
        The black widow spider is identified by a red hourglass on it\'s abdomen. Only the female bites, and it has a neurotoxic venom. The initial pain is not severe, but severe local pain rapidly develops. The pain gradually spreads over the entire body and settles in the abdomen and legs. Abdominal cramps and progressive nausea, vomiting, and a rash may occur. Weakness, tremors, sweating, and salivation may occur. Anaphylactic reactions can occur. Symptoms may worsen for the next three days and then begin to subside for the next week. Treat for shock. Be ready to perform CPR.
        Clean and dress the bite area to reduce the risk of infection. An antivenom is available.\n

        The funnel web spider is a large brown or gray spider found in Australia. The symptoms and the treatment for its bite are identical to the black widow spider.\n

        The brown house spider or brown recluse spider is a small, light brown spider identified by a dark brown violin on its back. There is no pain, or so little pain, that usually a victim is not aware of the bite. Within a few hours a painful red area with a mottled cyanotic center appears. Necrosis does not occur in all bites, but usually in 3 to 4 days, a star-shaped, firm area of deep purple discoloration appears at the bite site. The area turns dark and mummified in a week or two.
        The margins separate and the scab falls off, leaving an open ulcer. Secondary infection and regional swollen lymph glands usually become visible at this stage. The outstanding characteristic of the brown recluse bite is an ulcer that does not heal but persists for weeks or months. In addition to the ulcer, there is often a systemic reaction that is serious and may lead to death. Reactions (fever, chills, joint pain, vomiting, and a generalized rash) occur chiefly in children or debilitated persons.\n

        Tarantulas are large, hairy spiders found mainly in the tropics. Most do not inject venom, but some South American species do. They have large fangs. If bitten, pain and bleeding are certain, and infection is likely. Treat a tarantula bite as for any open wound, and try to prevent infection. If symptoms of poisoning appear, treat as for the bite of the black widow spider.\n

    </string>
    <string name="medical_scorpions_content">
        Scorpions are all poisonous. There are two different reactions, depending on the species:\n

        \u2022 Severe local reaction only, with pain and swelling around the area of the sting. Possible prickly sensation around the mouth and a thick-feeling tongue.\n
        \u2022 Severe systemic reaction, with little or no visible local reaction. Local pain may be present. Systemic reaction includes respiratory difficulties, thick-feeling tongue, body spasms, drooling, gastric distention, double vision, blindness, involuntary rapid movement of the eyeballs, involuntary urination and defecation, and heart failure. Death is rare, occurring mainly in children and adults with high blood pressure or illnesses.\n
        Treat scorpion stings as you would a black widow bite.\n
    </string>
    <string name="medical_snakebite_title">SNAKEBITES</string>
    <string name="medical_snakebite_content">
        The chance of a snakebite in a survival situation is rather small, if you are familiar with the various types of snakes and their habitats. However, it could happen and you should know how to treat a snakebite. Deaths from snakebites are rare. More than half of snakebite victims have little or no poisoning, and only about one-quarter develop serious systemic poisoning.
        However, the chance of a snakebite in a survival situation can affect morale, and failure to take preventive measures or failure to treat a snakebite properly can result in needless tragedy.\n

        The primary concern in the treatment of snakebite is to limit the amount of eventual tissue destruction around the bite area.\n

        A bite wound, regardless of the type of animal that inflicted it, can become infected from bacteria in the animal\'s mouth.
        With nonpoisonous as well as poisonous snakebites, this local infection is responsible for a large part of the residual damage that results.\n

        Snake venoms not only contain poisons that attack the victim\'s central nervous system (neurotoxins) and blood circulation (hemotoxins), but also digestive enzymes (cytotoxins) to aid in digesting their prey.
        These poisons can cause a very large area of tissue death, leaving a large open wound. This condition could lead to the need for eventual amputation if not treated.\n

        Shock and panic in a person bitten by a snake can also affect the person\'s recovery. Excitement, hysteria, and panic can speed up the circulation, causing the body to absorb the toxin quickly.
        Signs of shock occur within the first 30 minutes after the bite.\n

        Before you start treating a snakebite, determine whether the snake was poisonous or nonpoisonous.
        Bites from a nonpoisonous snake will show rows of teeth. Bites from a poisonous snake may have rows of teeth showing, but will have one or more distinctive puncture marks caused by fang penetration. Symptoms of a poisonous bite may be spontaneous bleeding from the nose and anus, blood in the urine, pain at the site of the bite, and swelling at the site of the bite within a few minutes or up to 2 hours later.\n

        Breathing difficulty, paralysis, weakness, twitching, and numbness are also signs of neurotoxic venoms. These signs usually appear 1.5 to 2 hours after the bite.\n

        If you determine that a poisonous snake bit an individual, take the following steps:\n

        \u2022 Reassure the victim and keep him still.\n
        \u2022 Set up for shock and force fluids or give by intravenous (IV) means.\n
        \u2022 Remove watches, rings, bracelets, or other constricting items.\n
        \u2022 Clean the bite area.\n
        \u2022 Maintain an airway (especially if bitten near the face or neck) and be prepared to administer mouth-to-mouth resuscitation or CPR.\n
        \u2022 Use a constricting band between the wound and the heart.\n
        \u2022 Immobilize the site.\n
        \u2022 Remove the poison as soon as possible by using a mechanical suction device. Do not squeeze the site of the bite.\n
        You should also remember four very important guidelines during the treatment of snakebites. <b>Do not:</b>>\n

        \u2022 Give the victim alcoholic beverages or tobacco products. Never give atropine! - Give morphine or other central nervous system (CNS) depressors.\n
        \u2022 Make any deep cuts at the bite site. Cutting opens capillaries that in turn open a direct route into the blood stream for venom and infection.
        \nNOTE: If medical treatment is over 1 hour away, make an incision (no longer than 6 millimeters [1/4 inch] and no deeper than 3 millimeters [1/8 inch]) over each puncture, cutting just deep enough to enlarge the fang opening, but only through the first or second layer of skin. Place a suction cup over the bite so that you have a good vacuum seal. Suction the bite site 3 to 4 times. Suction for a MINIMUM of 30 MINUTES. Use mouth suction only as a last resort and only if you do not have open sores in your mouth.
        Spit the envenomed blood out and rinse your mouth with water. This method will draw out 25 to 30 percent of the venom.\n

        \u2022 Don\'t put your hands on your face or rub your eyes, as venom may be on your hands. Venom may cause blindness.\n
        \u2022 Break open the large blisters that form around the bite site.\n
        After caring for the victim as described above, take the following actions to minimize local effects:\n

        \u2022 If infection appears, keep the wound open and clean.\n
        \u2022 Use heat after 24 to 48 hours to help prevent the spread of local infection. Heat also helps to draw out an infection.\n
        \u2022 Keep the wound covered with a dry, sterile dressing.\n
        \u2022 Have the victim drink large amounts of fluids until the infection is gone.\n
    </string>
</resources>